Guide to the Edward Isaac Lending Papers ALBA.068
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Edward Isaac Lending Papers
1937-1995, (Bulk 1978-1995)
bulk
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Lending, Edward Isaac, 1912-2003
ALBA.068
1.5 Linear Feet (3 boxes)
Edward Isaac Lending (1912-2003) fought with the International Brigades in Spain and later served in the United States Army during World War II. This collection includes Lending’s correspondence with veterans (primarily dating from the 1970s and 1980s); writings, which include articles, letters to editors and typescripts for speaking engagements; as well as a small number of documents dating from the Spanish Civil War and World War II periods.
Provenance
The Edward Isaac Lending Papers were donated to the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives between 1978 and 1994 by Edward Isaac Lending. This collection came to New York University in January 2001 as part of the original acquisition of ALBA collections, formerly housed at Brandeis University.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Historical/Biographical Note
Isaac Edward Lending was born March 24, 1912 and raised in the Bronx. His father, who ran a textile trimmings business, was a religious Jew and early member of the Zionist Organization of America. As a young man, Lending switched the order of his first and middle names, and was known thereafter as Edward Isaac Lending.
Lending studied journalism and business at City College of New York and New York University, but never completed his degree. In 1935 he joined the Communist Party and in 1937, at 27 years old, he departed for Spain aboard the Ile de France to join the International Brigades in fighting the Spanish Civil War. Over the next 21 months, Lending played a variety of roles in the war. He fought and was wounded in the Battle of Brunete. When he recovered, he was promoted to sergeant and fought in the Battles of Quinto and Belchite. In a break from fighting, Lending edited Brigade newspaper Our Fight and worked with volunteer Robert Steck in the Cultural Commission organizing a theatrical troop to entertain rearguard units. In December 1937, Lending volunteered for anti-aircraft service, joining the German Dimitrov Battery in the air defense of Barcelona.
After returning to the U.S. in December 1938, Lending became a member of the Executive Board of the Veterans of the Abraham Brigade (VALB). In 1943, he enlisted in the U.S. Army and served in World War II, putting his anti-aircraft experience to use in Belgium and Holland. During Lending's service an Army Service Forces investigation reported on his political activities. The report concluded that Lending was to be barred from attending Officer Candidate School as well as from performing a host of security-related duties. He was, however, granted an honorable discharge in 1946.
Lending pursued his political goals through journalism and public speaking, meanwhile making his living in sales and advertising in New York City. He married Jean Strunsky in 1949 and lived in Mexico City between 1950 and 1952. In 1960 he married Florence Davis. Their only child together died of Tay-Sachs Disease at age three.
While Lending had been devoted to the Communist Party between 1935 and 1943, his disillusionment with policy dictated by Soviet Party leadership had been growing at least since the Molotov-Ribbentrop Pact in 1939 to the point where he completely severed ties with the Party in 1943. Around this time Lending also grew critical of the VALB organization for what he perceived to be its rigid political orthodoxy. He gradually distanced himself from VALB and embarked upon what became a lifelong mission to persuade his former Spanish Civil War comrades, among others, to reject the Communist Party line. He gave talks, conducted correspondence with veterans, publicly challenged VALB in its publication, the Volunteer, and wrote numerous articles and letters to editors on the issue.
Another effort to which Lending devoted much time and energy was raising awareness of Jewish participation in the Spanish Civil War. Among other activities, he joined an endeavor led by veteran Irving Weissman to secure pension rights for struggling Polish Jewish veterans of the Botwin Company; and he initiated a campaign to commemorate Jewish fighters in Spain.
In 1978, after a brief period managing the family textile business, Lending retired and moved with Florence to Florida. The couple made frequent trips to Israel to be with Lending's stepson and family.
Lending died in Florida on September 24, 2003 at the age of 91.
Scope and Content Note
Series I, Correspondence.
This series comprises Lending’s incoming and outgoing correspondence primarily written in the late 1970s and the 1980s. All of Lending’s correspondence reflects the deep impression the Spanish Civil War made on him. In letters with Victor Berch (archivist of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archive at Brandeis University) and Peter Carroll (while Carroll was researching his book Odyssey of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade), among others, Lending recounts tales of battles, revisits the intricate political controversies of the period, memorializes fallen comrades and analyzes the impact that the war had on his life and politics. Many of the letters reflect Lending’s lifelong project to disabuse others, especially former Spanish Civil War comrades, of their allegiance to what he considered to be the hypocrisy and betrayal of Communism. Veterans with whom Lending corresponded include Moe Fishman, John Gerassi, Manny Harriman, Ben Iceland, Charles Nusser, Albert Prago, Abe Osheroff and George Watt. Other of Lending’s correspondence focuses upon his efforts to gain public recognition for Jewish participation in the Spanish Civil War. Correspondence also includes exchanges with political philosopher Sidney Hook; with veteran David Miller, who conducted an extensive interview with Lending (see Series II for transcript); with Morris Schappes, editor of Jewish Currents; and with Irving Weissman. A file of Lending’s letters to writer Ronald Radosh does not include Radosh’s replies.
Series II, Subject Files.
This series is comprised of documents primarily produced between the 1970s and 1990s. Exceptions include a hand-drawn "Wall-Paper" score chart from Spain rating the achievement of tasks by different Lincoln Brigade companies; a skit and poem, possibly written in conjunction with Robert Steck’s cultural commission; a portion of a diary by an unidentified volunteer; and an Army Service Forces investigation of Lending’s Communist activities conducted in 1944, during his service in World War II. A partial transcript of an interview with Lending conducted by veteran David Miller covers Lending’s childhood, his political dawning in the 1930s, a period spent working at the socialist Camp Unity, and encounters with political orthodoxy in Spain that fed his growing disenchantment with the Communist Party. (The audiotapes associated with this transcript have been separated into the non-print collection; consult staff for access.)
Evidence of Lending’s criticism of VALB includes a negative analysis of a VALB-sponsored proposal to develop a high school curriculum on the history of the Abraham Lincoln Brigades.
A cross-section of Lending’s writings are represented here, including articles published in Jewish Currents, the Florida Sun-Sentinel, Horizon and the Volunteer; as well as numerous letters to editors. Other writings include a typescript about anti-aircraft battle that appears to be based in part upon a memoir written by comrade Jim Persoff (this memoir appears elsewhere in this series); and typescripts for public speaking engagements.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically within each series.
Organized into 2 series:
Missing Title
I, Correspondence
II, Subject files
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
ALBA collections at the Tamiment Library.
Separated Material
Six audiotapes and three photographs from the Spanish Civil War period have been transferred from the Edward Isaac Lending Papers to the non-print section of the ALBA collection in the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives.
Drafts (documents); Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Personal narratives.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |x Participation, Polish.; Typescripts.; Personal papers.; Research (document genres).; Diaries; Biography files.; Correspondence.; Barcelona (Spain); Mt. Juic (Spain); Brunete, Battle of, Brunete, Spain, 1937.; Articles.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |x Aerial operations.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Campaigns.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |v Biography.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |x Participation, Jewish.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- International brigades.; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Brigada Internacional, XV; Hook, Sidney, 1902-1989; Watt, George, 1913-1994; Weissman, Irving, 1905-; Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives; Geiser, Carl; Carroll, Peter N.; Berch, Victor A.; Fishman, Moses (Moe), 1916-; Harriman, Manny.; Persoff, James.; Osheroff, Abe.; Miller, David, 1908-1977; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade; Lending, Edward Isaac, 1912-2003; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade. Historical Commission; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Abraham Lincoln Battalion; Iceland, Benjamin, 1910-1990; Schappes, Morris U. (Morris Urman), 1907-
- Series I: Correspondence
  - Correspondence: General, Jan 1970-Mar 1995 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bedrick, Ron, undated, Apr 1990-Aug 1993 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Berch, Victor, Apr 1980-Nov 1996 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Brooks, Christopher, Jul 1993-May 1995 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Carroll, Peter, Jun 1991-Aug 1994 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Chesler, Frank, Dec 1978-Aug 1980 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Colow, Maury, Aug 1968-Oct 1968, Oct 1991 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Fishman, Moe, Dec 1961, Oct 1995 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Gerassi, John, Feb 1980-Apr 1980 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Harriman, Manny, Sep 1978-Nov 1978 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Hendricks, Jeffrey, Oct 1990-Dec 1990 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Hook, Sidney, Jan 1988-Jul 1989 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Iceland, Ben, Mar 1979-Nov 1989 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Kaufman, Sidney, Sep 1988-Jan 1995 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Lamb, Leonard, Aug 1975-Mar 1980 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Marr, Eric (U.S. Holocaust Memorial Museum), Nov 1993-Sep 1994 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Miller, David, Feb 1974-Nov 1977 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Nusser, Charles, Feb 1985-Nov 1992 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Osheroff, Abe, undated, Dec 1983-May 1995 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Prago, Albert, May 1979-Apr 1982 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Radosh, Ronald, Apr 1986-Mar 1995 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Ross, Adolph, Oct 1984-Nov 1985 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Schappes, Morris ( Jewish Currents), Feb 1980-May 1995 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Smith, Randall (Pete), undated, Apr 1979-Jan 1982 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Steck, Robert, undated, Aug 1979-Mar 1987 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Watt, George, Oct 1979-Feb 1992 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Weissman, Irving, undated, Mar 1985-May 1995 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Series II: Subject Files
  - Abraham Lincoln Brigade Film Project: The Good Fight, Jan 1982-Apr 1984 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Asociacion de Ex-Presos y Represalindos Politicos: Spanish reparations effort, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Chisholm, Malcolm, Aug 1989-Sep 1990 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - City College Volunteers in Spain, undated, May 1978 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Cohen, Morris, May 1991-Jun 1991 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Drawings of Children by "Paquita", undated
  - Geiser, Carl: on Cuba, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Geiser, Carl: Prisoners of the Good Fight project, undated, Dec 1980-Jan 1981 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - German Democratic Republic: Report by Spanish Civil War Veteran, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - International conference on the Spanish Civil War, Apr 1979 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Jewish Immigration to Palestine: Basque participation, Feb 1992 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Jewish Veterans: General, undated, Jan 1992-Sep 1994 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Jewish Veterans: Mt. Juic, Barcelona memorial, undated, Dec 1989-Feb 1994 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Jewish Veterans: Plans for reunion and memorial, undated, Nov 1982-Jun 1984 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Lending, Edward: Army Service Forces investigation of, Jun 1944 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Lending, Edward: Biographical, undated, Aug 1994 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Lending, Edward: Transcript of audiotaped interview by David Miller, Jul 1975 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - March on Washington: No war in the Middle East, Jan 1991 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Morrissey and Ibrahim vs. Joseph Curran et al (pamphlet), 1980 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Obituaries and Memorials, May 1960, Dec 1977-Jan 1995 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Persoff, James: Spanish Civil War memoir—Description of battle, ca.1937 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Spanish Civil War: Articles about, undated, Feb 1969-Nov 1982 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Spanish Civil War: Diary (unidentified, photocopy), ca.1937 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Spanish Civil War Historical Society, undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Spanish Civil War: Poem and Skit, Jun 1938-Dec 1938 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Spanish Civil War: Postcards, ca.1937 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Spanish Civil War: Volunteer for Liberty (newspaper, w/note from Lending), July 1938 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Spanish Civil War: Wall-Paper Score Chart, Jan 1938 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Teachers Union: "Boys in Spain" Subscription form, ca.1937 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - VALB: Correspondence, undated, Oct 1972, Jan 1979-Jul-94 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - VALB: High school curriculum on Abraham Lincoln Brigade history, Dec 1989-Jan 1990 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - VALB: Historical Committee, Nov 1980-Nov 1981 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - VALB: Minutes, Dec 1980-Sep 1982 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - VALB: Pensions for Polish Veterans, undated, Sep 1972-Dec 1990 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - VALB: "Washington Merry-Go-Round", Apr 1943 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Writings: on Barcelona Reunion 1988 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Writings: "Chronicles of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade" (talk), Oct 1986 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Writings: "Jews Who Fought" (talk), Jan 1991 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Writings: "Joe’s Long Shadow" (on Joe Dallet), undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Writings: Letters to the Editor, undated, Sep 1973-Mar 1991 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Writings: "Los Rompedores", undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Writings: "Los Rompedores" -- Correspondence regarding, Apr 1985-Nov 1985 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Writings: "Nostalgia", Sep 1982 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Writings: Published – General, May 1976-Apr 1990 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Writings: Published -- Sun-Sentinel(South Florida), Mar 1983-Apr 1995 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Writings: on Spanish Civil War, Description of Battle, undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Writings: on Spanish Civil War (Florida Atlantic University talk), Oct 1986 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Writings: Submitted to The Volunteer, undated, Jul 1978-Aug 1994 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Writings: "Textbooks in the Trenches", undated (Box 3, Folder 25)